Good morning. Today's דף daf is פ"ב. Peh-Bet. We'll be soon beginning
a new, the final פרק, perek, but before that, we have to
finish the old one. So, we pick up on the bottom of
פ"א עמוד ב'. Peh-Aleph amud bet. אמר
רבי יוחנן Amar Rabbi Yochanan and this is about a גט קרח,
get kereach, a גט get with the, which was a גט מקושר,
get mekushar, a bald גט get which started with the גט מקושר
get mekushar which was one that they made for כהנים Kohanim in
order to slow down the process of divorcing their wives. I'm imagining
my little illustration went away but never mind. People, what they do
is they write a few lines and then fold it over so
that this part would be written and then they would fold it
over on a blank spot, okay? And then the עדים edim would
sign here and then they would like write a few lines,
how would you do this? And then you would fold it over
again like that, I guess you would, you'd probably fold it the,
oh yeah, you have to do it like that, right, okay. And
then you write a few lines here and you basically make an
accordion, okay? And they would, so each one of these things, right,
each one of these things would be like, would be, would be
sewn up. In here would be writing, you know, writing and blank,
writing and blank and each of these would be sewn up and
then there'd be a signature on each one of the things of
the accordion. And they'd require a minimum of three of those, so
three signatures, and the גט קרח get kereach is that the guy
made, I don't know, ten of them and he did not get
all of those folds signed, he only got nine signed or something
like that. And then we're going to talk, the ברייתא braita discusses
he had one fewer signed, we'll talk in a minute about other
scenarios. Anyway, and in that case what do you, it's פסול pasul
and it's very weightily פסול, pasul, at least according to רבי מאיר,
Rabbi Meir, תצא והוולד ממזר, tetzei v'havlad mamzer, the whole thing, at
least that's רבי מאיר's Rabbi Meir's position. But then ironically, even though
it's so, such a weighty problem, you can actually fill those blanks
even with פסולי עדים. psulei edim. Maybe only a קרוב, karov, maybe
any פסול עד. pasul ed. But that's as long as you have
the basic three that חז"ל Chazal demanded. And the end of the
day yesterday we discussed let's say you have two, which is enough
דאורייתא, d'Oraita, does the third one have to be כשר kasher as
well? And the גמרא Gemara clearly really wanted to say it had
to be כשר kasher but it had to deal with some ברייתות
braitot that indicated that maybe it could be a קרוב. karov. Okay,
but that's the first שיטה, shita, the basic two or three have
to be totally כשר kasher and the others have to be filled
out and if they're not, the גט get is פסול, pasul, but
they can be filled out with פסולי עדים. psulei edim. Yes. Two
or three? We're about to look at that, whether there's a specific
location for the כשר kasher ones. Okay, so let's take a look.
Two lines from the bottom of פ"א עמוד ב'. Peh-Aleph amud bet.
אמר רבי יוחנן, Amar Rabbi Yochanan, לא הוכשרו בו אלא עד אחד
קרוב בלבד. lo huchsharu bo ela ed echad karov bilvad.
Now we're spelling this out. So the fact that we allow you
to fill in those blank spots with a non-כשר kasher witness, that's
one blank spot, all the other folds have to be כשר עדים.
kasher edim. אבל תרי לא, Aval trey lo, all the others have
to be כשר kasher and here's why: דילמא אתי לקיומי בתרי קרובים
וחד כשר dilma ati l'kiyumei bitrei krovim v'chad kasher
because what בית דין Beis Din will do is they'll have this
גט get with ten folds and ten signatures and they'll need to
be מקיים mekayem the signatures, right, they'll need to validate them. So
they'll say does anybody know any of these signatures? And they'll put
out a little announcement in the paper, okay, and then people will
come and they'll validate three of the ten signatures. Well, if you
allow more than one פסול pasul to sign, they might be validating,
they might be allowing this woman to remarry on the basis of
two פסול pasul signatures, right? But if you only allow one פסול
pasul person to sign, then any three signatures that they're going to
use, two of them will be כשר עדים. kasher edim. So that's
why he says you can only have one because if you have
two people that are relative, they will come to you maybe by
chance they'll use those as the signatures that they're going to validate
and go by and we'll מתיר matir this woman on the basis
of non-valid testimony. You know you can at some point validate the
other ones. Maybe, maybe not, maybe you'll find out you can never
validate them. אמר אביי, Amar Abaye, מתניתין נמי דייקא, matniten nami dika,
that's also can be read by a close read of our משנה,
mishna, or the ברייתא braita actually, דקמדלג ותני חד חד d'kamdaleg v'tani
chad chad because yesterday the ברייתא braita we quoted was if you
have seven folds and six עדים, edim, six folds and five עדים,
edim, five folds and four עדים, edim, okay, you can fill in
the other one with a פסול pasul witness. So it keeps on
speaking about just missing one עד, ed, it never spoke of missing
more than one עד. ed. שמע מינה, Shma mina, so the גמרא
Gemara says you know what, that's a good proof. Okay, one second.
Yes. So when we say, so someone says כולכם, kulchem, right, so
there has to be a case where they're not more than two,
not more than one קרוב karov in? In כולכם kulchem they all
have to be כשרים, ksherim, they all should be כשר. kasher. Right.
Oh, you can't have any קרוב karov at all. Right. Which is
why תוספות Tosafot asks this whole thing is גזירת כולכם, gezeirat kulchem,
why do you allow a קרוב? karov? But okay, okay. The גמרא
Gemara says like this, שמע מינה, shma mina, okay, good, so we're
only allowed one פסול. pasul. Now, אמר אביי, Amar Abaye, now this
is going to get back to the question Michael asked, שמע מינה
האי קרוב חסם shma mina hai karov chasam אי בעי בין בתחילה
בין באמצע בין בסוף. i ba'ei bein betchila bein be'emtza bein b'sof.
We can infer from this that when the relative
signed, he can sign wherever he wants, there's no particular location where
you allow the פסול pasul signature. Why is that? How do you
know? How do you know that? מאי מדלא קבע ליה מקום. Mai
midlo kavlei makom. שמע מינה, Shma mina, okay, you know why? Because
it didn't say. That's what the ברייתא Braita say, you can fill
it out if a blank spot is left at the end. If
a blank spot is left in the middle, right? So the fact
that it didn't tell you where it could be filled out shows
you that he can fill out that any that that with the
fact that we allow one פסול pasul to sign can be in
any of the folds. All right. Now, ושמע מינה, V'shma mina, you
could also infer from this
מכל תלתא דמקיימין mikol tlasa d'mekaymin that we the בית דין beis
din will use any three signatures that we can validate. We don't
have they don't have to be three consecutive signatures. How do you
know that? I thought that was part of your question before, but
then, yeah, and we won't say that you need to have רצופין,
ratsufin, we won't say that you need to validate three consecutive signatures.
דאי סלקא דעתך בעינן רצופין, De'i salka daitach ba'inan ratsufin, if you
need to if they need to be consecutive, לקבע ליה מקום להאי
קרוב likba leih makom lehai karov בתחילה או באמצע או בסוף bitichla
o b'emtza o b'sof ולכשר ביה טובא, v'lichshar beih tuvah, so then
let him sign in a in a particular place to sign in
the beginning, middle, and end, and then it'll you can allow a
lot of פסול pasul signatures. Now what does this exactly mean? There's
a couple ways you can interpret it. רש"י Rashi basically go says
the following. What רש"י Rashi says, which maybe doesn't work so literally
in the language of the גמרא, Gemara, but it's a brilliant point.
רש"י Rashi basically says
that why don't we just say that you have to you can
have a פסול pasul sign as long as it's after two כשר
kasher signatures? So if you do that, right, then you have כשר,
kasher, כשר, kasher, פסול. pasul. Now I want a פסול pasul to
sign here. He says, no, no, no, you can't. A פסול pasul
can only come after two כשר kasher signatures. Okay, כשר, kasher, כשר,
kasher, פסול, pasul, and that's the way you go through the גט.
get. Now if you demanded that you use consecutive signatures, there's no
way you can get two פסולים. psulim. Any three signatures is going
to have two כשרים, ksherim, right? Because you only allow two כשרים
ksherim immediately juxtaposed to a פסול. pasul. So if you if we
had a principle that we'd only use consecutive signatures, we would say
פסולים psulim can sign as many times as they want as long
as there are two כשר kasher signatures before them. Since we don't
say that, since we say that פסולים psulim can only sign once,
you you see that בית דין beis din will use any three
signatures. And since they'll use any three that they can validate, we
can't allow two פסול pasul to sign because then two of those
three might be פסול. pasul. I don't know how long it took
רש"י Rashi to work that out. I don't know, but if you
look at the end of רש"י, Rashi, Michael thinks it's very easy.
If you look at the end of רש"י, Rashi, רש"י Rashi says
the following. רש"י Rashi says...
Look at the last line of רש"י Rashi before the end of
the פרק. perek. כעין זו עיקרה של סוגיא זו K'ein zu ikara
shel sugya zu ולא שמעתיה כן. v'lo shimatiha ken.
That wasn't the tradition I had to explain this, but but it's
what I figured out is the best פשט pshat of this סוגיא.
sugya. אלא כביאורה בקונטרס מורי הזקן. Ela k'veura b'kuntres mori hazaken. So
apparently what רש"י Rashi is saying is like the version I heard
was what my רבי Rebbe wrote in his notebook and he wrote
in his פירוש peirush on the גמרא, Gemara, but that didn't make
any sense to me. So this is what I'm telling you what
the סוגיא sugya really means. Okay, anyway, so back to the גמרא.
Gemara. So the גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay, טובא. Tuvah. כי
אתא לקמיה דרבי אמי, Ki ata l'kamei d'Rabbi Ammi, when it came
to רבי אמי Rabbi Ammi and a גט get that had a
blank spot in it, אמר ליה צא והשלימה לאו אפילו מן השוק.
amar leih tzei v'hashleima lav afilu min hashuk. Go get a even
a slave to fill in the last one, פוסק paskening who that
like like בן ננס Ben Nanos was it? Yeah, בן ננס. Ben
Nanos. It said that one פסול pasul signature could be even a
slave. Okay, הדרן עלך הניירות. Hadran alach haniyarot. So all these are,
you know, equally important, these signatures. Because like otherwise I would have
thought like there's something like a
sort of sets the wrong tone to have a פסול pasul as
the first signature. Yeah, I understand that. It's a good point. I
don't know what to tell you. It's a good point. Now I
do want to say by the way, the idea that you could
have פסול pasul signatures if that's understood to be the context and
we don't why don't we just say נמצא אחד מהם קרוב או
פסול, nimtza echad mehem karov o pasul, right? One of the list
is פסול, pasul, פסולס pasuls the whole group. So presumably once there's
an understood context that that person isn't part of the group, he's
just being done for a different purpose, then it does not פסול
pasul the other signatures. Now that's very interesting because the רמ"א Rama
brings down that there was a practice by כתובות ksuvos that after
they would have the two כשר kasher signatures, they would get קרובים
krovim and פסולים psulim and whatever just as a way of like
honoring the חתן chassan and כלה. kallah. You just like pass around
the כתובה ksuva and everybody would sign their name to it, even
though they would be קרובים krovim or whatnot. And we don't say
that that was קרוב או פסול karov o pasul because it was
understood that that was functioning differently. Okay, so that's very interesting here
because you do have a פסול pasul signature and it doesn't invalidate
the rest. And as now, of course in the רמ"א's Rama case,
you needed the two immediately ones after the כתובה ksuva to be
כשר. kasher. All right. Let's take a look at now the next
פרק. perek. Okay, המגרש את אשתו. Hamgaresh es ishto. Now we turn
to a another fascinating set of scenarios that we have not dealt
with until now. המגרש את אשתו ואמר לה, Hamgaresh es ishto v'amar
lah, he divorces his wife and he said to her, הרי את
מותרת לכל אדם אלא לפלוני. harei at muteres l'chol adam ela l'ploni.
You are permissible with this גט get to marry any man except
Frank. I got a I'm not so sure about you and Frank
and therefore I'm not saying you are permissible to marry any man
except him. Okay, is that a good גט? get? So Michael says
no. רבי אליעזר מתיר. Rabbi Eliezer matir. רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says
it's a good גט. get. וחכמים אוסרין, VeChachamim osrin, and the Rabbis
say it's not good. Rabbi, some people say it's not a כריתות?
Kritut? No, right, exactly.
כיצד יעשה, Keitzad ya'aseh, so if it's no good what should
he do? יטלנה ממנה ויחזור ויתננה לה, Yitlena mimena veyachzor veyitnena lah,
take it and take it from her and then give it back
to her and say הרי את מותרת לכל אדם, Harei at muteret
lechol adam, behold you are מותרת לכל אדם. muteret lechol adam. Meaning,
the חדוש chiddush here is, and we've seen scenarios like this in
the past, that the גט get doesn't get used up. If it
was an invalid act of delivering the גט, get, the act of
the act of divorce is invalid, but the חפצא cheftza of the
גט, get, the object of the גט, get, is still a valid
instrument, and this in the גט get itself, which is the next
line, כתבו בתוכו, katvo betocho, if it was written in the גט,
get, אף על פי שחזר ומחקו פסול, af al pi shechazar umachako
pasul, even if you erase it, it's פסול, pasul, because the whole
עדים edim signed on an invalid כריתות krisus and so on. I
mean if you erased it before the עדים edim signed it and
you validated the fact that you had erased it, maybe, but once
if you created it in the גט, get, you made an invalid
instrument. But if the instrument was valid and you just gave it
in the wrong way, then you can re-give it. Okay, so that
is the case of when you exclude, she's not מותרת לכל אדם.
muteret lechol adam. Now the גמרא's Gemara going to ask the fundamental
question of what is the nature of this exclusion? Yes. I was
just going to say, is what's happening now they're exploring one of
the limitations of conditionality? Well that's exactly the question the גמרא's Gemara
going to ask. Let's see the גמרא. Gemara. What's this, a guy
with someone she could marry anyway, that's why it wouldn't be a
different... What? Just a guy with someone she could marry anyway, that's
why it wouldn't be a different... Like if he was a כהן,
Kohen, you mean, and he said חוץ מפלוני chutz miploni and she
was אסורה asurah to a כהן. Kohen. It's an interesting question. Like
that's an interesting question. Right? Yeah, that's a good question. What? I
mean she's still married
anyway. Well, according to the חכמים, Chachamim, that it doesn't work. According
to חכמים Chachamim it doesn't work, she's totally married, right? ריח הגט.
reiach haget. Right, yeah, sure. Well you mean is it a ריח
הגט reiach haget problem? We're going to get to that. Okay, that's
another good question. But halachically she's 100% married according to חכמים. Chachamim.
Whether there's a כהונה kehunah issue we'll get to.
Now Michael raised a good question which I hadn't thought about. I
mean look there's still a difference even if you say you're not
מותר muter to כהנים Kohanim because what then the husband is saying
is if you sleep with a כהן Kohen it's adultery as opposed
to, and even and forget
it, right? I mean there's the whole question רמב"ם Rambam ראב"ד, Ra'avad,
is the איסור issur of כהונה kehunah only through marriage or even
through sex outside of marriage? Right? So number one is, if he
says you're not מותר muter to a כהן, Kohen, it forbids her
even in sex outside of marriage, number one. But number two, what
he's also saying is is that that turns out into adultery, whereas
otherwise her איסור issur was only an איסור כהונה issur kehunah to
a כהן, Kohen, an איסור לאו. issur lav. Just for your followers.
Oh, okay, that's an interesting question. So the גמרא's Gemara going to
deal with that. Okay, that's a good question, right? So Michael says
what if she says except for somebody that anyway it would be
completely אסור assur to marry, it would be a חייב כרת, chayav
kares, marriage wouldn't be תופס, tofes, so excluding that person didn't have
any bigger effect. Okay, so the גמרא's Gemara going to do it.
But except for a כהן, Kohen, I think, you know, definitely would,
because that would have obviously much more of a profound effect. Okay,
let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. איבעיא להו. Iba'ya lehu.
האי אלא חוץ Hai ela chutz או על מנת? o al menat?
Does it mean except for ראובן, Reuven, does that mean it should
take effect except, you know, with the exclusion of ראובן Reuven vis-a-vis
ראובן Reuven you're an אשת איש? eishet ish? The חלות, chalut, you
know, the sort of the impact of the גט, get, the fact
that it is limited to excludes ראובן, Reuven, or does it mean
על מנת, al menat, or does it mean on the condition? You
are 100% divorced from everybody in the world on the condition that
you don't marry or sleep with ראובן. Reuven. But if you marry
or sleep with ראובן, Reuven, then retroactively you were never divorced from
anyone. Right? I mean I'll give you an easy נפקא מינה. nafka
mina. She sleeps with שמעון Shimon and then she sleeps with ראובן.
Reuven. Right? If it means על מנת, al menat, then once she
slept with ראובן Reuven she also committed adultery with שמעון. Shimon. Right?
But if it means חוץ, chutz, then assuming you know, then with
ראובן Reuven it would be an act of adultery but with שמעון
Shimon it would not. Is that clear? No? Not clear? Really? Alright,
here's ראובן. Reuven.
Does he have a neck? Yeah. Here's שמעון. Shimon. Okay, now I'm
saying assuming it does work, meaning assuming we'll take like רבי אליעזר.
Rabbi Eliezer. Okay,
I don't care. Okay, here's the woman. Okay, now if it says
חוץ מראובן, chutz miReuven, okay, so for ראובן Reuven you are still
considered to be my wife, okay, so she sleeps with שמעון, Shimon,
that's not an act of adultery. She sleeps with ראובן, Reuven, no
he says vis-a-vis ראובן Reuven you're still my wife, that is an
act of adultery. If however he says on the condition, על מנת,
al menat, okay, then what happens? She sleeps with שמעון Shimon and
she sleeps with ראובן. Reuven. Once she slept with ראובן, Reuven, retroactively
even her sleeping with שמעון Shimon was an act of adultery, because
then retroactively she was never divorced.
Okay, so does it mean for ראובן Reuven you're my wife, for
everybody else you're not my wife, or does it mean for everybody
you're not my wife on the condition you never sleep with ראובן?
Reuven? Okay, so if it's חוץ ממנו, chutz mimeno, she collected כתובה
ketubah from her original husband because she is technically... well you mean
according to רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer. Yeah, because if only one guy
is walking around on the planet... man she's still vis-à-vis him married
to her husband. Well, that's really the question of כריתות, krisus, that's
why they would debate this. Okay, so let's see the גמרא. Gemara.
So I actually framed it as what would be the נפקא מינא
nafka mina assuming it would work, right? But the גמרא Gemara wants
to ask why are they debating? So if I reframe it this
way, so I say which case, if you had a pick, is
obviously be not a good גט? get? If it means what, על
מנת al mnat or חוץ? chutz?
חוץ! chutz! How can you divorce somebody without totally freeing her to
everyone? A גט get means מותרת לכל אדם, mutteres lechol adam, right?
על מנת al mnat then maybe it could work. The end result
is she can't sleep with ראובן, Reuven, but the basic, you know,
effect of the גט get is that it makes her completely divorced.
So that's the גמרא's Gemara's question. Alright, so that's the גמרא's Gemara's
question. And maybe it make a difference if ראובן Reuven died, because
like there was a problem with the actual, you know, from the
onset, like, you know, it was a bad גט. get. Yeah, yeah,
I'm talking about even in רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, assuming it worked,
but they would say, oh once he dies, and it's okay. No,
because then it's a problem from the outset, from the outset. Okay.
הי חוץ אלא חוץ או על מנת? חוץ, ובחוץ היא דפליגי רבנן
עליה דרבי אליעזר. Hai chutz ela chutz o al mnat? Chutz, uvechutz
hi d’pligi rabbanan alei d’Rabbi Eliezer. When you say you're divorced except
for ראובן, Reuven, okay, that's where they debate, דשייר לה בגט, d’shayer
lah b’get, the גט get is not completely effective, it's not effective
vis-à-vis ראובן. Reuven. אבל בעל מנת, Aval b’al mnat, if you say
on the condition that you don't marry or sleep with ראובן, Reuven,
מודי ליה, modeh lei, they would agree. End result is she can't
sleep with ראובן, Reuven, but the basic effect of the גט get
is that she's permitted to everyone. That's one way of framing it.
Then you really have to understand רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer. How does
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer allow a גט get to only be 99
percent effective and not 100 percent effective?
Okay. Okay, אבל בעל מנת מודי ליה מידי דהוה אכל תנאי דעלמא,
Aval b’al mnat modeh lei midei d’hava a’chol tnai d’alma, like all
תנאי דעלמא tnai d’alma work. Okay. או דילמא, O dilma, or do
you say? So that's the way that you could, you know, that
would very much limit it and be a huge חידוש chiddush for
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer that חוץ chutz would work. או דילמא, Od
dilma, or do you say, no, על מנת, al mnat, they're debating
על מנת. al mnat. ובעל מנת הוא דפליגי רבי אליעזר ורבנן. U’v’al
mnat hu d’pligi Rabbi Eliezer v’rabbanan. And that's where they debate because
there רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says it's just a condition and the
רבנן rabbanan say it's not just a condition, it's a condition that
has the effect of not allowing her to marry anybody else, or
not allowing her to marry this one person. אבל בחוץ, Aval b’chutz,
but in a case where you actually said it would not be
effective vis-à-vis ראובן, Reuven, מודה, modeh, even רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer would
agree that that's not a good גט, get, דשייר לה בגט, d’shayer
lah b’get, okay, that he did not make, that the גט get
is not complete. Okay. So I think it makes much, much more
sense to say they debate על מנת, al mnat, right? Because it's
so hard to understand רבי אליעזר's Rabbi Eliezer's position if they're debating
חוץ. chutz. Let's see what the גמרא Gemara says. Now the גמרא
Gemara is going to bring what is like I think one of
the most bizarre ראיות. rayos. Let's take a look. אמר רבינא, Amar
Ravina, of course, I'm sure I say that all the time. אמר
רבינא תא שמע, Amar Ravina ta shema, come and hear. כל הבתים
מיטמאים בנגעים, Kol habatim mitamim b’negaim, all houses can become טמא tamei
through spots, you know, of this נגע צרעת, nega tzaraas, אלא של
עובדי כוכבים, ela shel ovdei kochavim, except for the houses of non-Jews.
So what does the word אלא ela there mean? Okay. Same אלא
ela as our משנה. mishna. הרי את מותרת לכל אדם אלא לראובן.
Harei at muteres lechol adam ela l’Reuven. Now,
of course, how the תנא tanna uses the word אלא ela and
what does it mean when it's clear in context as opposed to
how does it mean when a person says it and it's not
clear in context. Fine. But the גמרא Gemara is going to use
this as proof what the word אלא ela means. Okay. אי אמרת
בשלמא חוץ הוא, Ei amart b’shlama chutz hu, if אלא ela meant
with the exception of, so שפיר, shapir, all houses are טמא, tamei,
can become טמא tamei with נגעים negaim with the exception of houses
of non-Jews. That's what אלא ela usually means. אלא אי אמרת על
מנת הוא, Ela ei amart al mnat hu, but if אלא ela
meant only if, right? How you eat אלא, ela, with the exception
of or only if? Right? With the exception of ראובן Reuven or
only if you don't marry ראובן. Reuven. So if it means only
if, so what does that mean? All houses are מיטמא בנגעים mitama
b’negaim only if houses of non-Jews are מיטמא בנגעים. mitama b’negaim. What?
So על מנת דלא מיטמו בתי עובדי כוכבים הוא דמיטמו בתי ישראל.
Al mnat d’lo mitamu batei ovdei kochavim hu d’mitamu batei Yisrael. I'm
sorry, on the condition, only if the houses of non-Jews won't be
מיטמא בנגעים, mitama b’negaim, הוא דמיטמו בתי ישראל, hu d’mitamu batei Yisrael,
then houses of Jews will be
טמא. tamei. Only on the following condition? Like what? הא מיטמו בתי
עובדי כוכבים לא מיטמו בתי ישראל. Ha mitamu batei ovdei kochavim lo
mitamu batei Yisrael. If the houses of non-Jews could become
טמא, tamei, then the houses of Jews would not become טמא. tamei.
It's of course absurd. Who are we making this condition with? God?
ועוד בתי עובדי כוכבים מי מיטמו V’od batei ovdei kochavim mi mitamu?
What do you mean on the condition that they don't become טמא?
tamei? They don't become טמא! tamei! והתניא ונתתי נגע צרעת בבית ארץ
אחוזתכם, V’hatanya v’nasati nega tzaraas b’veis eretz achuzaschem, I will give it
in the house in the land of your inheritance. ארץ אחוזתכם מיטמא
בנגעים ואין בתי עובדי כוכבים מיטמא בנגעים. Eretz achuzaschem mitama b’negaim v’ein
batei ovdei kochavim mitama b’negaim. Only the place that like you owned,
that you have an inheritance in. Houses of non-Jews, even in ארץ
ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, are not מיטמא בנגעים. mitama b’negaim. So anyway, so
אלא שמע מינה חוץ. ela shma mina chutz. Obviously in that משנה
mishna it means with the exception of. שמע מינה. Shma mina. So
if חוץ chutz means that משנה mishna with the exception of, here
too it means with the exception of and not only if, not
on the condition that. Okay, which is a big חידוש chiddush now
that we're saying that if our משנה mishna means with the exception
of, then maybe they agree על מנת al mnat works, which is
fine,
but... Even when you say the גט get is not effective vis-a-vis
a particular person, it's still a good גט, get, which is a
big חידוש. chiddush. Okay, now the גמרא Gemara is going to say.
But that other possible reading actually does exist in a ברייתא. braita.
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this, מתניתין דלא כי האי
תנא. matnitin d'lo ke-hai tanna. Our משנה mishna which we've established that
they're debating when you say חוץ, chutz, with the exception of, is
not like the following ברייתא braita that frames the debate in a
different way. דתניא, detanya, we taught in the ברייתא, braita, אמר רבי
יוסי ברבי יהודה, amar Rabbi Yose be-Rabbi Yehuda, לא נחלקו רבי אליעזר
וחכמים lo nechleku Rabbi Eliezer va-chachamim על המגרש את אשתו ואמר לה
הרי את מותרת לכל אדם חוץ מפלוני. al ha-megaraish et ishto ve-amar
lah harei at muteret le-chol adam chutz mi-ploni. If you would say
you're permitted to everybody except for ראובן, Reuven, nobody disagrees, שאינה מגורשת.
she-eina megureshet. Of course she's not divorced. That's not fully effective. על
מה נחלקו? al mah nechleku? What was the debate? על המגרש את
אשתו ואמר לה הרי את מותרת לכל אדם על מנת שלא תנשאי
לפלוני. al ha-megaraish et ishto ve-amar lah harei at muteret le-chol adam
al menat she-lo tinnasi le-ploni. If you say you're permissible to everybody
על מנת al menat on the condition that you don't marry, there
at least there's something to talk about. שרבי אליעזר מתיר לכל אדם.
she-Rabbi Eliezer mattir le-chol adam. He says that works. חוץ מאותו איש,
chutz me-oto ish, don't sleep with that guy because then retroactively you'll
never have been divorced, but go ahead and marry anyone you want.
וחכמים אוסרים, va-chachamim osrim, and the חכמים chachamim forbid it. מאי טעמא
דרבי אליעזר? mai ta'ama de-Rabbi Eliezer? What's the reason רבי אליעזר Rabbi
Eliezer thinks it's good? What do you mean? מידי דהוה אכל תנאי
דעלמא, midi de-havai a-chol tnai de-alma, like any condition works. ורבנן, ve-rabbanan,
and what would the rabbis say back? No. כל תנאי דעלמא לא
שייר לה בגט, kol tnai de-alma lo shiyyer lah be-get, any normal
condition he's not,
meaning it's true. At a conceptual level, the גט get is 100%
effective, but in the practical world in which we live, she's not
going to have the permission to, in practice she will not be
permitted to marry anyone she wants and therefore that, even if it's
just practically prevents it and not at a sort of at a
conceptual level, at a, you know, excludes it, nevertheless the practical prevention
makes it a not a good כריתות. kritut.
הכא שייר לה בגט. hacha shiyyer lah be-get. Here he actually, the
גט get does not, you know, leave something over. Even again, even
if in principle it's totally effective, in practice it does not allow
her. Now by the way, I should say that תוספות Tosafot has
an interesting discussion whether with על מנת, al menat, the גמרא's Gemara
example of על מנת al menat is on the condition you don't
marry so and so. תוספות Tosafot says let's say you said it
on the condition that you don't marry and don't have sex with
so and so. Would רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer agree then? Maybe that,
you know, is completely like making it forbidden, like the גט get
has no effect, right, in terms of that other person. So תוספות
Tosafot assumes, he goes through back and forth but he basically assumes
we're talking even if you say on the condition that you don't
marry or don't have sex with so and so. So the effect
totally excludes that person, but conceptually the גט get is, you know,
the גט get is effective. It's just a condition. So רבי אליעזר
Rabbi Eliezer says I'm going to just look at it as a
condition. I don't care if in practice it has that effect. And
the חכמים chachamim say no, if in practice it doesn't make her
permissible to that person, it's not a good גט. get. All right.
Yes? How can... even in theory how do you make a condition
that contradicts what's allowed? Either way she's not allowed because she's married,
so that would be a double negative. Right. And if so, how
can you insert a condition that would prevent the גט get from
being a valid כריתות? kritut?
Well that's what the חכמים chachamim say. But רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer
says... yeah, but he says conceptually that exists outside of the גט.
get. The גט get makes her totally permitted and this is just
something external to it which is if you want the גט get
to work you'll follow the following conditions. But for when the גט
get works it works 100%. As long as I haven't slept with
ראובן, Reuven, the גט get makes me permissible to ראובן. Reuven. So
I mean isn't there a complication just in the logic? Yeah, I
understand. That's what the חכמים chachamim say, but you can understand רבי
אליעזר's Rabbi Eliezer position. I can understand it. Right? I can! You
know, it's because it's not because again, like, in principle the גט...
get... it's a question of whether you look at something in principle
or in practice, you know. I'm selling you my house. It's yours,
you could do whatever you want. Just don't paint the living room
red.
That's the condition to buy the house. That's different because here in
the definition of the גט get itself... right, there is a difference...
right, the very nature of it is to give somebody that power...
that's right... and to make a condition... right, of course... so that...
yeah, that's exactly... so can you, can you bracket something which is
intrinsic to the definition of the instrumentality of the גט get and
still have it be a whole effect? It's an interesting מחלוקת. machloket.
It's a really interesting... yeah, I mean, I don't know, I guess
a comparison would be let's say I sold you a... I don't
know, let's say like I sold you something like that was a...
I don't know, I sold you an olive tree, okay? Or maybe
it could even make it a bigger example. I sold it to
you לפירותיה. le-firoteha. It was clear your whole goal was to get
the פירות. peirot. And I said you are entitled to those to
all those פירות, peirot, I'm selling you the פירות peirot of the
olive tree on condition that you don't eat 10% of them. Right.
So could you so could you say that? Right. So that's the
question. Okay.
Now the גמרא Gemara says like
this, okay, ומתניתין דאוקימנא בחוץ, u-matnitin d'okimna be-chutz, מאי טעמא דרבי אליעזר?
mai ta'ama de-Rabbi Eliezer? Now, if it's one thing... But if you're
saying that it works even when you say חוץ chutz according to
רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, how could a גט get not be a
hundred percent effective? So the גמרא Gemara says, is it the whole
point of a גט get to sever her from her past husband?
This is not severing her. So אמר רב ינאי משום זקן אחד,
Amar Rav Yannai mishum zaken echad, which is interesting, רב ינאי Rav
Yannai said in the name of a certain elder, whoever that elder
was, אמר קרא, Amar kra, the verse says: ויצאה מביתו והלכה והיתה
לאיש אחר. V'yatzah mibeito v'halcha v'hayta l'ish acher.
She leaves his house and she goes and marries one other man,
another man. אפילו לא הותרה אלא לאיש אחד הרי זו מגורשת. Afilu
lo hutra ela l'ish achad harei zu megureshet. Oh,
you see that a גט get can work even if it only
allows her to marry one man. Okay, so a גט get does
not have to make her הרי את מותרת לכל אדם. Harei at
muteret l'chol adam. What do you mean לכל אדם? l'chol adam? The
תורה Torah says והלכה לאיש אחר. v'halcha l'ish acher. Maybe it's a
גט get even if it just makes her permissible to one man.
Okay, which is a very bizarre idea. It's both a bizarre idea
that a גט get conceptually, like, you know, we always think of
a גט get as severing, but it's also a bizarre idea to
think about what the end result is that you're left with because
think for a minute, what are you left with as an end
result besides the question of the nature of a גט? get? What
is the nature of this marriage? You're married to me vis-a-vis this
person and not vis-a-vis somebody else? Right? So it's both a question
of what is a גט, get, a גט get normally we think
has to sever, and it's also a question of I don't understand,
isn't a marriage like either all or nothing? How can you have,
like, you know, how can you be a little pregnant? How can
you have a little bit of a marriage? How could it be
vis-a-vis this person, not vis-a-vis that person? Okay, which is now what's
going to lead the גמרא Gemara to its other question of: Can
you לכתחילה lechatchila create a marriage that looks like this if you
can actually have it at the end?
Okay, רבנן, Rabbanan, what would the rabbis say? There's a little bit
of a question here about the גירסא, girsa, but anyway, we'll read
it with the parentheses. אמרי טעמא דרבי אליעזר, Amri ta'ama d'Rabbi Eliezer,
so we'll take out the parentheses, רבנן, Rabbanan, האי איש, hai ish,
what does it mean לאיש אחר? l'ish acher? Sounds like one man
is still a good גט. get. So they'll tell you, no, לכל
איש ואיש. l'chol ish v'ish. No, no, no. איש אחר ish acher
means whoever she wants to marry. Doesn't mean she now goes to
a particular man. It means a גט get has to allow her
to now marry whoever she wants, and if it can't let her
marry whoever she wants, it's not a good גט. get. I'm interested
that the language of ספר כריתות Sefer Kritut has not come up
explicitly. Right. No, that's like taken for granted, I think, that that
is the problem, which is why רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer has to,
the גמרא Gemara says, "How could חוץ chutz work? Right?" Now you're
right, it could have said, "How could חוץ chutz work? Don't you
need ספר כריתות?" Sefer Kritut? But I think that that's like implicit,
which is why רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer has to quote a פסוק
pasuk to defend his position. Okay, רבי יוחנן אמר, Rabbi Yochanan amar,
טעמא דרבי אליעזר מהכא, ta'ama d'Rabbi Eliezer meihacha, a different verse to
defend רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer. ואישה גרושה מאישה לא יקחו, v'isha grusha
me'isha lo yikachu, גרושה מאישה, grusha me'isha, excuse me, לא יקחו. lo
yikachu.
And a woman divorced from her husband a כהן kohen cannot marry.
So what does that mean? Why does it have to say "divorced
from her husband"? Why doesn't it just say ואישה גרושה לא יקחו?
v'isha grusha lo yikachu? So to tell you, אפילו לא נתגרשה אלא
מאישה נפסלה מן הכהונה. afilu lo nitgarsha ela me'isha nifsela min hakehuna.
Let's say the husband gave her a גט get and said, הרי
את מגורשת ממני ואי את מותרת לשום אדם. Harei at megureshet mimeni
v'i at muteret l'shum adam. Okay?
So she's only divorced from her husband but she's not permissible to
anyone. So רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says according to this פסוק, pasuk,
that would actually, that's her, גרושה מאישה. grusha me'isha. She's not permissible
to anybody else but she's גרושה מאישה, grusha me'isha, whatever that means,
I
don't know, okay? And therefore she's פסול לכהונה. pasul l'khuna. Now that
is actually a concept of ריח הגט. reach haget. We've had ריח
הגט reach haget before. But normally we assume that ריח הגט reach
haget is רבנן. Rabbanan. Certain types of גיטין Gittin are close enough
to being כשר kasher that it creates a problem for כהנים kohanim
at a רבנן Rabbanan level. He shouldn't marry a woman who had
such a גט. get. It looks like she's divorced. This דרשה drasha
is actually saying that there's a ריח הגט reach haget מדאורייתא. mide'oraita.
That if a man gave a גט get to his wife and
said, הרי את מגורשת ממני ואי את מותרת לשום אדם, Harei at
megureshet mimeni v'i at muteret l'shum adam, then she actually would be
פסולה psula to a כהן kohen מן התורה min haTorah because she's
גרושה מאישה. grusha me'isha. And the argument is as follows, as תוספות
Tosafot and רש"י Rashi pretty much say, it says nobody is thinking
that in that case this woman would actually be really מגורשת. megureshet.
Okay. The example that תוספות Tosafot gives is like the נפקא מינה
nafka mina תוספות Tosafot says is, oh, let's say the husband died.
Okay? Let's say he divorced her but said, "You're not מותרת לכל
אדם," muteret l'chol adam, and then he died. Could the brother do
יבום? yibum? Okay? So תוספות Tosafot says it's פשיטא pashitah the brother
could do יבום. yibum. Like it's פשיטא pashitah that this doesn't work.
Okay? This doesn't do anything. But here's a חידוש. chiddush. If it
doesn't, if the תורה Torah is still going to say it's a
כהן kohen problem, if you could never exclude anything from a גט,
get, it wouldn't even be a כהן kohen problem. It would be
so absurdly invalid that it wouldn't even be a problem for כהנים.
kohanim. So if the תורה Torah is saying when you exclude the
whole world, it's a, it's not a good גט, get, but it's
a problem for כהנים, kohanim, that suggests that if you excluded some
people but not everybody, it really would be a good גט. get.
You hear the argument? Sort of? Yes? Okay. Meaning, if it's so
absurd, if you can't even exclude one person... How could we think
if you exclude the whole world, it would be a כהן Cohen
problem? So what you’re saying, if you exclude the whole world, it’s
a כהן Cohen problem, that suggests that if you excluded just one
person, it might actually be a real, it might actually really work.
Okay. So that’s the דרשה. drasha. And אמר המהווה גיתותיה amar hamaveh
gitoteiha אלא
משנפסלה מכהונה ela mishenifsela mikhuna אמר המהווה גיתותיה. amar hamaveh gitoteiha. You
see that when you exclude somebody, now in the case when you
exclude everybody, but when you exclude somebody, it actually could be a
good גט. get. ורבנן Verabanan and the Rabbis will say, no, איסור
כהונה שאני. issur kehuna shani. Nah, this is a כהן Cohen issue,
so it’s a ריח הגט, reyach haget, so that doesn’t prove anything
about, you know, about what really would be a good גט. get.
You can’t make any inferences from this. Okay, so that’s the debate.
Now the גמרא Gemara says the following.
בעי רבי אבא בקידושין היכי. ba’ei Rabbi Abba bekidushin haichi. What would
be the story in a case of קידושין? kidushin? If according to
רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, if you could end with a 90, with
a 10% marriage or a 5% marriage, vis-a-vis you’re married to me
vis-a-vis ראובן Reuven not to the rest of the world, until now
we thought marriage had to be all or nothing, so can you
create that reality as well? So what would be the story? תיבעי
לרבי אליעזר תיבעי לרבנן. tiba’ei leRabbi Eliezer tiba’ei leRabanan. You could ask
it whether according to רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer whether according to the
רבנן. Rabanan. תיבעי לרבי אליעזר, tiba’ei leRabbi Eliezer, you could ask it
according to רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer. עד כאן לא קאמר רבי אליעזר
הכא אלא משום דכתיב קרא. ad kan lo ka’amar Rabbi Eliezer hacha
ela mishum dechtiv kra.
Maybe this weird idea that you don’t have to fully divorce, that’s
because you have a פסוק pasuk that tells you that you can
exclude a person. Okay? דכתיב קרא. dechtiv kra. אבל התם קניין מעליא
בעינן. aval hatam kinyan ma’alya ba’inan.
But maybe by קידושין kidushin it’s all or nothing like we always
thought, it’s just a special חידוש chiddush by a גט. get. או
דילמא o dilma or do you say no, ויצאה והיתה. veyatza vehayta.
It links קידושין kidushin to גירושין, gerushin, and if by גירושין gerushin
you can not have a full גירושין, gerushin, by קידושין kidushin you
can have a non-full קידושין. kidushin. Okay, that’s one read. ותיבעי לרבנן
vetiba’ei leRabanan and you can even ask maybe the Rabbis, which would
be bizarre, would be more allowed this phenomenon by קידושין kidushin than
by גיטין. gittin. עד כאן לא קאמרי רבנן התם. ad kan lo
ka’amri Rabanan hatam. Why do they not allow this phenomenon here הכא?
hacha? אלא דבעינן כריתות וליכא. ela deba’inan kritut velayka. There you go
though, it’s because we need כריתות, kritut, of course here it can’t
work, it has to totally sever. אבל התם קניין כל דהו. aval
hatam kinyan kol dahu. But maybe we would say by קידושין kidushin
any act that connects her to you, that connects the woman to
the man, constitutes קידושין kidushin even if it’s not a full and
an exclusive relationship. Okay, it’s really bizarre. Okay, bizarre plus. So it
looks like what the גמרא Gemara is going to get to what
it looks like. או דילמא o dilma or do we say no,
ויצאה והיתה, veyatza vehayta,
no, קידושין kidushin is like גיטין. gittin. So גמרא Gemara says: לבתר
דבעי לה הדר פשטה. lebatarey deba’ei lah hadar pashtah. After he raised
the question, he came to the conclusion,
בין לרבי אליעזר בין לרבנן, bein leRabbi Eliezer bein leRabanan, בעינן ויצאה
והיתה. ba’inan veyatza vehayta. We link קידושין kidushin to גט, get, which
means that for the רבנן Rabanan if it doesn’t work by a
גט get it doesn’t work by קידושין. kidushin. But it means, listen
to this crazy idea, that according to רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, the
same way you could say הרי את מגורשת ממני וחוץ
מראובן, harei at megureshet mimeni v'chutz miReuven, you could also say to
a woman: הרי את מקודשת לי חוץ מראובן. harei at mekudeshet li
chutz miReuven. So now all of a sudden we thought, you know,
Judaism only recognized, you know, polygamy, but it also, what’s called polyandry,
right? In theory here now you could have a woman married to
two men, right? So you’re מותרת mutteret vis-a-vis חוץ מראובן, chutz miReuven,
so she which she can now what, have sex with ראובן Reuven
and it wouldn’t be adultery? And now could she marry ראובן? Reuven?
So she could marry ראובן Reuven and ראובן Reuven would say, if
ראובן Reuven says, what גמרא Gemara is going to get to it,
שמעון Shimon says: הרי את
מקודשת לי חוץ מראובן, harei at mekudeshet li chutz miReuven, and ראובן
Reuven says: הרי את מקודשת לי חוץ משמעון. harei at mekudeshet li
chutz miShimon. So neither of them are excluding the other person, right?
Each of them are allowing that their קידושין kidushin doesn't affect the
other guy in the picture. So then is she מותרת mutteret to
sleep with both of them, right? If she’s married to two men?
That’s what you might have according to רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer. So
let’s take a look. דאורייתא. de’oraita. Yeah. I’m not advocating it. Okay.
Let’s take a look.
Okay. אמר אביי אם תמצא לומר איתא לדרבי אבא. Amar Abaye im
timtza lomar ita ledirbi Abba. If what רבי אבא Rabbi Abba said
is correct, right, that this issue about that it applies you can
infer from גיטין gittin to קידושין. kidushin. So בא ראובן וקידשה חוץ
משמעון. ba Reuven vekidsah chutz miShimon. ראובן Reuven said you’re married to
me except for שמעון. Shimon. שמעון Shimon you can continue to sleep
with. Okay. ובא שמעון וקידשה חוץ מראובן, uva Shimon vekidsah chutz miReuven,
as the bizarre scenario I just gave you, and שמעון Shimon said
and said you’re married to me but that doesn’t exclude ראובן. Reuven.
So each of them allows for the other man to be in
the picture. Okay. Now the גמרא Gemara does not ask the first
thing I want to know, which is, but does that mean she
can sleep with either guy and it’s not adultery? Presumably yes. Okay,
now the גמרא Gemara though has to follow... it’s also brothers. So
that’s an additional... yeah, I mean that’s true. Right, right, that’s true.
This is a case of brothers as we’re about to see. Yeah,
so but you know it’s not a man married to two sisters,
it’s a woman married to two brothers. התורה HaTorah never forbids that.
Because the התורה HaTorah never has a woman married to two men.
Okay, anyway, but right, now we’re actually going to look at the
יבום yibbum case. ובא שמעון וקידשה חוץ מראובן, uva Shimon vekidsah chutz
miReuven, I did, ומתו שניהם. umetu sheneihem. Now they both died.
Now לוי, Levi, who's the third brother, can come and do יבום,
yibum, okay? Because he's got now a זיקה zika from ראובן Reuven
and a זיקה zika from שמעון. Shimon. Now we've only got a
bit of a problem though. What's the problem? The problem is you
might remember from יבמות Yevamos that you cannot have זיקת שני יבמים.
zikas shenei yevamim. You cannot do יבום yibum if this woman you're
now connected to her through two זיקות. zikas. What would be the
case? The case would be, okay,
oh, we still could have had this woman here. Okay, so this
woman dies, okay, I'm sorry,
let's do שמעון Shimon and לוי, Levi, and she's married to ראובן,
Reuven, okay? And they're all brothers. ראובן Reuven dies. שמעון Shimon comes
ahead and he does מאמר. ma'amar. People remember what מאמר ma'amar is?
It's sort of
like a rabbinic type of קידושין kidushin יבום yibum etc., which basically
means it's not דאורייתא de'oraisa effective, but it
basically, some say at least a rabbinic level, we'll look at them
as if they're married. And then okay, and then שמעון Shimon dies.
Now לוי Levi here, another brother, he has a מצוה mitzvah of
יבום yibum on this woman. He has a מצוה mitzvah of יבום
yibum from two directions, from his first from ראובן Reuven he has
a מצוה mitzvah of יבום yibum and from שמעון. Shimon. Okay now,
if שמעון Shimon had done יבום, yibum, ראובן Reuven would be out
of the picture because then he would just supplant ראובן. Reuven. But
because he didn't do יבום, yibum, ראובן Reuven is still in the
picture, right? The obligation vis-a-vis ראובן Reuven has not yet been satisfied.
So even though there's only rabbinic, since for לוי Levi he has
a connection through שמעון Shimon and through ראובן, Reuven, that's considered זיקת
שני יבמים zikas shenei yevamim and rabbinically you know he cannot do
יבום. yibum. So what the גמרא Gemara wants to know is can
we get a זיקת שני יבמים zikas shenei yevamim going on a
דאורייתא de'oraisa level? Okay, and the way it would work on a
דאורייתא de'oraisa level is, right,
okay,
she's married to both of these guys the way we just saw.
This marriage doesn't exclude him and his marriage doesn't exclude her. And
then they both die. So now he's obligated both through ראובן Reuven
and through שמעון, Shimon, should be a problem. Okay, and the גמרא
Gemara is going to say it's not. Why is it not a
problem? Let's take a look. Because two husbands are like one husband.
Ah, maybe. Let's see whose name is going to be. I don't
know. So we'll see, let's see what the גמרא Gemara says, okay?
ואינני קורא בה v'einani korei bah I don't call
it אשת שני מתים. eishes shenei meisim. מאי טעמא, mai ta'ama, why?
קידושי דראובן אהנו, kidushei d'reuven ahannu, because ראובן's Reuven's marriage was binding.
קידושי דשמעון לא אהנו. kidushei d'shimon lo ahannu. שמעון's Shimon's marriage was
not binding. Why was שמעון's Shimon's marriage not binding? You said that
שמעון Shimon was still in the picture. Because, because it's not that
it wasn't binding, it's that what the גמרא Gemara is saying is
it wasn't effective. Meaning, when שמעון Shimon said הרי את מקודשת לי
חוץ מראובן, harei at mekudeshes li chutz mi'reuven, the fact that she
was married to שמעון Shimon had no implications to the rest of
the world, right? Before שמעון Shimon did anything, before שמעון Shimon did
anything, she was אסורה asura to the rest of the world except
for שמעון, Shimon, right? שמעון Shimon now marries her, she remains אסורה
asura to the rest of the world except for שמעון. Shimon. שמעון's
Shimon's marriage did not affect her status vis-a-vis the rest of the
world. Is that clear? Yes? Yes? No? Everybody with me here? Okay.
When ראובן Reuven married her and said חוץ משמעון, chutz mi'shimon, she
couldn't marry anyone except שמעון. Shimon. שמעון Shimon marries her, says חוץ
מראובן. chutz mi'reuven. Did that marriage make any difference about her status?
Did it affect who she could marry? No.
Okay. So she's already married to ראובן. Reuven. She already is אסורה
asura to everybody else. So those קידושין kidushin to שמעון Shimon shouldn't
be חל. chal. That's what the גמרא Gemara is saying. So it's
bizarre that the גמרא Gemara uses the example of יבום, yibum, presumably
it's using it as a test case to prove if it's חל
chal or not. But it's a way of actually saying that it's
not חל. chal. Okay, another way the גמרא Gemara could have said
it is let's say שמעון Shimon is not ראובן's Reuven's brother and
שמעון Shimon died, whatever you know there's no מצוה mitzvah of יבום
yibum or whatever. Anyway, but it's a way of saying it's not
חל chal because it did not have an effect. Now I'm going
to tell you how it could have an effect. Let's say ראובן
Reuven said חוץ משמעון chutz mi'shimon and Frank over here. Those two
you can, those two you're still okay with, okay? And then שמעון
Shimon comes and says חוץ מפרנק. chutz mi'frank. Okay, so that marriage
did something. It excluded her from Frank. I mean, not חוץ מפרנק,
chutz mi'frank, אסורה לכל העולם חוץ מראובן, asura l'chol ha'olam chutz mi'reuven,
but you are אסורה asura to Frank, okay? So the marriage here
made her אסורה asura to Frank. So that marriage had some effect.
You guys with me here? Yeah. So in that case, she really
would be married both to ראובן Reuven and שמעון. Shimon. The גמרא
Gemara does not have a fundamental problem that she could be married
to both guys again within this way of thinking, and presumably that
she could sleep with both guys even though she's married to the
other one. The גמרא's Gemara's problem is that the second act didn't
add anything to her status. But if that second קידושין kidushin was
it kicked Frank out of the picture because this guy allowed for
Frank as well, okay, then actually it would be effective and she'd
be married to both of them. Or possible to forget Frank, leave
him. Yeah, according to the first scenario, you got both guys under
the חופה Chuppah and they say the statement of קידושין Kiddushin simultaneously.
That wouldn't work because they're mutually exclusive. Why is the... why isn't
there a problem of whose child it would be? Why don't they
raise that? Yeah, I mean that's you're right, I mean that's what
you want to start asking, all those questions. What do you mean
whose child it would be? The one who was the father of
the child. No, but as oh, you mean for the יבום Yibum
issue? Because we're not interested, let's forget the יבום. Yibum. We're going
if you're allowing even the concept happily married all three of them.
Right, so whose child is it? What do you mean whose child?
It's the child of whoever's father, whoever was the father. How do
they know who's the father? That's a good question. Okay, it's a
good question. They'll do a genetic test thing.
They'll do a genetic test thing! And it couldn't be answered? It
could if one guy was out of town or whatever. But okay,
alright, so then we could have interesting questions of how do you
split the ירושה. Yerusha. Alright, moving on, this is like this is
like, you know, מנחת חינוך Minchat Chinuch heavy here. Okay, anyway, moving
on. We can say the same question because here you don't know
whose name you're perpetuating. It's the same kind of yeah, but that's
not I mean I understand all the issues you're raising, but the
גמרא Gemara like isn't even up to that yet. Alright. Okay, so
now the גמרא Gemara says like this,
ואלא אשת שני מתים היכי משכחת לה. Ve'ela eshet shenei metim heichi
mashkachat lah. Okay, how could you get a case? כגון שבא ראובן
וקידשה חוץ משמעון ובא שמעון וקידשה סתם. Kegon sheba Reuven vekidsha chutz
mi'Shimon uva Shimon vekidsha stam. Now, I gave you a case where
she really could be married at the same time to two guys.
But let's see what the גמרא's Gemara going to say. כגון שבא
ראובן וקידשה חוץ משמעון ובא שמעון וקידשה סתם. Kegon sheba Reuven vekidsha
chutz mi'Shimon uva Shimon vekidsha stam. So Shimon came and he said
you're married to me and you're אסורה asura to everyone including Reuven.
So Shimon was coming and kicking Reuven out of the picture. וקידושי
דראובן אהנו למיסרה אכולי עלמא Vekiddushei de'Reuven ahani lemisra achulei alma the
קידושין Kiddushin of Reuven made her forbidden to everyone except Shimon. וקידושי
דשמעון אהנו למיסרה אראובן Vekiddushei de'Shimon ahani lemisra a'Reuven and then Shimon's
effect made her forbidden to Reuven. Of course, the pressure here is
you're saying wait a minute, if Shimon succeeds in making her forbidden
to Reuven, what would you expect the consequence would be?
Shimon comes and marries her and says you're אסורה asura to everyone
including Reuven, your husband. What do you think the consequence would be?
That maybe Reuven would stop being her husband, right? No, it can't
be. Why not? Because that's not that's not. So now you're married
to Reuven but you're אסורה asura to have sex with him because
you're also married to me. Wait.
You think the second one is חל? chal? Because because the second
one is חל chal because it's uprooting the rights of the first
one. One of them is חל, chal, right? The two of them
can't exist at the same time. That's what you say.
Alright, well let's see what the גמרא Gemara says. Okay, I think
what I would probably intuitively agree with you just in terms of
fairness, but let's see what the גמרא Gemara says. Alright, let's take
a look. בעי אביי Ba'ei Abaye אמר ליה. amar leh. Okay, וקידושי
שמעון אהנו למיסרה אראובן. Vekiddushei Shimon ahani lemisra a'Reuven.
So wait a minute.
No, oh,
so that question isn't in the גמרא, Gemara, that question is in
תוספות. Tosafot. Look at תוספות. Tosafot. כגון שבא ראובן וקידשה חוץ משמעון
Kegon sheba Reuven vekidsha chutz mi'Shimon ובא שמעון וקידשה סתם. uva Shimon
vekidsha stam. Says
תוספות, Tosafot, תימא לרבנו יצחק Teima le'Rabbeinu Yitzchak כשבא שמעון וקידשה סתם
אמאי לא פקע אישות דראובן kesheba Shimon vekidsha stam amai lo paka
ishut de'Reuven מה שמענו mah shamnu etcetera, etcetera. So he asks that
if you're basically making her excluded to Reuven, then that should push
Reuven out. What you're saying is, if you're making her excluded to
Reuven, that should make what you're doing ineffective. The גמרא Gemara imagines
that she could be married to Reuven and Shimon, but she can't
have sex with Shimon even though she's married to Reuven because Reuven
didn't exclude Shimon. But she can't have sex with Reuven because she's
married to Shimon and Shimon did exclude Reuven. Okay, so that's a
case where אשת שני מתים. eshet shenei metim. I don't know, to
me, I mean that's a big חידוש. chiddush. To me, once we're
dealing with this absurd scenario altogether, the easier case is that they
excluded one another, but the second one also, you know, also made
her אסורה asura to Frank, right? So each one had an effect.
This made her אסורה asura to the whole world except Shimon and
Frank. This made her אסורה asura to Frank and now but מותרת
muteret to Reuven. Okay, and now she's מותרת muteret to both of
her husbands. You've got a whole nice little polyandry going on there.
That's what I'm saying. According to רבנו יצחק, Rabbeinu Yitzchak, what he's
suggesting, just דרך הפקעת קידושין derech hafka'at kiddushin in this scenario, solve
the עגונה agunah problem by just simply having her marry someone else
and make this statement. That's
right. I mean essentially it's a הפקעת קידושין hafka'at kiddushin situation, that's
what... Yeah, but not in a way that we could implement. Okay,
no, theoretically, I hold the... I don't know how we're going to
implement it. בעי אביי. Ba'ei Abaye. Aren't עריות arayot דאורייתא, d'oraita, right?
Yeah. Right. How are they coming up with this example that's a
biblical prohibition? What's the biblical prohibition? Marrying two brothers. Where does it
say you can't marry... the תורה Torah says you can't marry two
brothers because the תורה Torah doesn't have a woman married to two
husbands.
Isn't there a whole list of who you're not... oh, you mean
why isn't she, if they're brothers, why isn't she when she's sleeping
with Shimon, sleeping with her husband's brother?
You've married a brother-in-law. Right, so that's true, so it's it also,
according to this scenario, would also be the איסור issur of אשת
איש. eshet ish. You're right. It would be the איסור issur of
husband's brother, but not of... married woman. But if ראובן Reuven and
שמעון Shimon weren't brothers? But they're making the... why? So they're making
the... Okay, but the גמרא Gemara isn't asking the question of what
if she sleeps with one of them? I'm asking the question. The
גמרא Gemara is just asking, 'Is she considered married? Does she have
a status of being married?' You know, you could come and say
that the גמרא, Gemara, חס ושלום, chas veshalom, she couldn't ever sleep
with both of them or whatever. The גמרא Gemara just wants to
know if, like, on paper she's considered married to them, but not
that she actually would be allowed to sleep with the other one.
Okay? Because the גמרא Gemara isn't asking who can she sleep with?
The גמרא Gemara is just asking who on paper is she married
to? and the obligations that are... Right, are they both חייב chayav
and share to... certain... עונה? onah? No, no, no, some of those
obligations are דאורייתא, de'oraisa, yeah. It's like a game of chess. I
know, I got it, I got it. But David makes an excellent
point, which is, right, which is that in the case of brothers
she can't sleep with שמעון Shimon because it's her husband's brother. But
if they're not brothers, then it would be okay. But again, I
do want to emphasize, I've been talking because I think it's the
first thing that all of us asks. One minute, if she's married
to two guys and they've excluded one another, so she can sleep
with either of them or with both of them? So the גמרא
Gemara has not addressed the question of who can she have sex
with. The גמרא Gemara just wants to know like on paper who
is she married to and the test case is the יבום yibum
case is one of those test cases for that. Who do we
define her as being married to? Okay, the גמרא Gemara hasn't addressed
the question of who can she sleep with. It's not about... the
question isn't about sex, the question is about like whose health insurance
can she get? There you go. Okay, so let's just read one
more question. Welcome to... right. בעי אביי. baei Abaye.
That's a good way of putting it. Okay, אמר לה, amar lah,
הרי את מותרת לכל אדם חוץ מראובן ושמעון. harei at muteres lechol
adam chutz miReuven veShimon. Okay, he excluded ראובן Reuven and שמעון. Shimon.
וחזר ואמר לה, vechazar veamar lah, לראובן ושמעון. leReuven veShimon. Okay, so
there was. He said, he gave her the גט. get. We're moving
away from קידושין, kiddushin, which was such a fun case. Okay, but
here he is, he gives her the גט get and says הרי
את מותרת לכל אדם חוץ מראובן ושמעון harei at muteres lechol adam
chutz miReuven veShimon and then before giving her the גט get he
said, right, לראובן ושמעון leReuven veShimon and he gives her the גט.
get. What do those words לראובן ושמעון leReuven veShimon mean in that
context? First he said חוץ מראובן ושמעון chutz miReuven veShimon and then
before he gave her the גט get he said לראובן ושמעון. leReuven
veShimon. So what did they mean? When he says וחזר ואמר לראובן
ושמעון, vechazar veamar leReuven veShimon, מהו? mahu? מי אמרינן, mi amrinan, מה
דאסר שרא? mah deasar shara? When you said חוץ מראובן ושמעון chutz
miReuven veShimon and then you said לראובן ושמעון, leReuven veShimon, you said,
'You know what? You're also מותר mutter for ראובן Reuven and שמעון.'
Shimon. I'm filling in the gaps. What I said you, the men
I said that you were still forbidden to, I'm now saying you're
permitted to. That's one way to read it.
או דילמא, o dilma, you say no, מה דאסר שרא ומה דשרא
אסר. mah deasar shara u'mah deshara asar. You completely flipped it. Right?
You said הרי את מותרת לכל אדם harei at muteres lechol adam
and then you said חוץ מראובן ושמעון chutz miReuven veShimon and then
you paused and you said לראובן ושמעון. leReuven veShimon. So maybe what
you're saying is you're מותר mutter to ראובן Reuven and שמעון Shimon
and אסור assur to everyone else. So you're totally flipping it. Okay.
אם תמצא לומר, im timtza lomar, if you say, right, מה דאסר
שרא, mah deasar shara, then no, no, no, לראובן ושמעון leReuven veShimon
means we're just filling in the gap. You're מותר mutter to everybody
including ראובן Reuven and שמעון. Shimon. Okay, let's say he said לראובן,
leReuven, מהו? mahu? הרי את מותרת לכל אדם חוץ מראובן ושמעון harei
at muteres lechol adam chutz miReuven veShimon and then he said לראובן.
leReuven. So what do we say about that? לראובן והוא הדין לשמעון.
leReuven vehu hadin leShimon. So ראובן Reuven and שמעון Shimon means and
you're also מותר mutter to ראובן Reuven and שמעון. Shimon. So what
if he just said לראובן? leReuven? When he says ראובן Reuven is
he just sort of, you know, speaking elliptically and he means, 'You
know what? You're מותר mutter to both of them
also.' והאי דקאמר לראובן משום דפתח ביה vehai dekamar leReuven mishum defasach
beih
because that was the first of the list. Okay, but he means
yeah, yeah, yeah, you're מותר mutter to all those guys as well.
או דילמא לראובן
דוקא? o dilma leReuven davka? No, maybe you're מותר mutter to ראובן
Reuven but you're still אסור assur to שמעון. Shimon. אם תמצא לומר
לראובן דוקא, im timtza lomar leReuven davka,
if when you say he said לראובן leReuven he meant no, I'm...
you're מותר mutter just to ראובן Reuven now but to שמעון Shimon
you remain אסור. assur. If he said לשמעון, leShimon, מהו? mahu? Why
he said הרי את מותרת לכל אדם חוץ מראובן ושמעון harei at
muteres lechol adam chutz miReuven veShimon and then he said לשמעון. leShimon.
Okay, so what does that mean? לשמעון
והוא הדין לראובן. leShimon vehu hadin leReuven. Now actually I mean שמעון
Shimon and
ראובן. Reuven. והאי דקאמר לשמעון משום דסליק מיניה. vehai dekamar לשמעון mishum
desalik mineih. It was the last word out of my mouth. I
said חוץ מראובן ושמעון chutz miReuven veShimon and then I said, 'No,
לשמעון.' leShimon. Okay, and that means everything I just said before, you're
מותר mutter to everyone. Okay, או דילמא לשמעון דוקא? o dilma leShimon
davka? No, maybe now you're מותר mutter to everybody and שמעון Shimon
but you're still אסור assur to ראובן. Reuven. בעי רב אשי, baei
Rav Ashi, רב אשי Rav Ashi wants to know, אף לשמעון, af
leShimon, מהו? mahu? He said הרי את מותרת לכל אדם חוץ מראובן
ושמעון harei at muteres lechol adam chutz miReuven veShimon and then he
said, 'You know what? אף לשמעון, af leShimon, even שמעון.' Shimon. So
what does even? Even שמעון Shimon and... so אף אראובן קאי? af
aReuven kai?
You know what? You're even מותר mutter to ראובן Reuven and even
to שמעון. Shimon. אף לשמעון af leShimon meaning ראובן Reuven and even
שמעון. Shimon. או דילמא אף אעלמא קאי? o dilma af a'alma kai?
You know what? You're מותר mutter to the whole world and even
you're מותר mutter to שמעון, Shimon, but still you're אסור assur to
ראובן. Reuven. תיקו. teiku. So we don't have the answer to any
of those. Now I want to just say, okay, I want to
say who is this question according to? It could be according to
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer and we want to know למעשה. lema'aseh. According
to רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer is she now מותרת mutteres to ראובן
Reuven and שמעון Shimon or אסורה assurah to ראובן Reuven and שמעון,
Shimon, right? That's one way of asking the question. The other question
could be according to the חכמים Chachamim that חוץ chutz doesn't work.
So if this follow-up statement filled the whole gaps, made her מותרת
mutteres to ראובן Reuven and שמעון, Shimon, it's a כשר גט. kasher
get. If the follow-up statement made her still אסורה assurah to one
of them, then it's a not כשר גט, kasher get, right? So...
Or you could ask this question according to the חכמים Chachamim to
say this filled the gaps and made her מותר mutar to everyone
and make it a כשר kosher גט, get, or does it not
fill the gaps and it's a פסול pasul גט? get? Or you
could ask it according to רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer. No, it's going
to be כשר kosher either way, but we just want to know
whether ראובן Reuven and שמעון Shimon can now marry her. All right,
so the גמרא Gemara ends with this question, but again the really
fascinating issue is how can you be not 100 percent, 50 percent
married, 90 percent married? What is that reality? Okay, more of this
tomorrow.